You will travel far, my little Kal-El.
.کال اِل کوچولوی من , تو به یه سفر دور خواهی رفت
But we will never leave you...
...اما هرگز ترکت نمی کنیم
... even in the face of our deaths.
.حتی موقعی که وقت مرگمون فرا برسه...
You will make my strength your own.
.تو قدرت منو مال خودت خواهی کرد
You will see my life through your eyes...
...زندگیم رو از درون چشمهات خواهی دید
... as your life will be seen through mine.
.همونطوری که زندگیت از طریق... .چشمهای من دیده خواهد شد
The son becomes the father, and the father the son.
,پسر , پدر میشه .و صاحب پسر
In spite of your past...
...با وجود گذشته ات
...I know you're a good man.
.میدونم که آدم خوبی هستی...
And all good men...
...و همه ی آدمهای خوب
...deserve a second chance.
.لایق یه فرصت دوباره هستند ...
From the moment I received your first letter...
از لحظه ای که اولین ...نامه تو دریافت کردم
...I knew you were not like the rest.
.میدونستم که استراحت رو دوست نداشتی...
You came from nothing...
...تو از ناکجاآباد میای
...and you worked so hard to get where you are.
و خیلی سخت تلاش کردی ... .تا بفهمی کجا هستی
You might have made a few mistakes.
.میتونی چند تا اشتباه داشته باشی
- Gertrude, for God's sake! - Damn it, Gertrude, let us in now!
!گِرتراد , بخاطر خدا- !لعنتی , گِرتراد , اجازه بده بیایم تو-
You said that if I helped you get out of prison...
گفتی که اگه بهت کمک ...کنم از زندان بیرون بیای
...you'd take care of me.
.میخواستی مواظبم باشی...
And you have.
.و بودی
You've shown me pleasures that I've never known.
تو خوبی هایی در حق من کردی .که دیگران هرگز نفهمیده اند
That's why you deserve...
...به همین دلیله که
...everything.
.سزاوار همه چیز هستی...
I love you...
...لِکس لاتر
...Lex Luthor.
.دوسِت دارم...
Gertrude, let us in. He's a crook.
.گِرتراد , بذار بیایم تو , اون شیاده
He doesn't love you, Gertrude!
!گِرتراد , دوسِت نداره
He's a monster! Gertrude!
!او یه هیولاست ! گِرتراد
- You can keep that. - Oh, God.
.میتونی نیگهش داری- .اوه , خدایا-
The rest is mine.
.باقیش ماله منه
We're done.
.تموم کردیم
Bye, Martha.
.خداحافظ , مارتا
Oh, Clark.
.اوه , کلارک
Oh, my boy.
.اوه , پسرم
Will you get that thing out of my face!
!از جلوی چشام دورش کن
Lex, your friends give me the creeps.
.لکس , دوستات این کریپ رو بهم دادند
Prison is a creepy place, Kitty.
.زندان محل وحشتناکیه , کیتی
One needs to make creepy friends in order to survive.
برای زنده موندن , احتیاج داره دوستای ترسناکی بسازه
Even a man with my vast talents is worth less inside...
هر یه مرد با بهترین استعدادهای ...من ارزششون کمتر از
...than a carton of cigarettes and a sharp piece of metal in your pocket.
یه کارتن سیگاره و ... .یه تیکه فلز تو جیبتونه
Do you know the story of Prometheus? No, of course you don't.
افسانه ی تیتان پسر پاپتوس رو میدونی ؟ .نه , معلومه که نمی دونی
Prometheus was a god who stole the power of fire from the other gods...
تیتان خدایی بود که قدرت آتش ...رو از سایر خدایان ربود
...and gave control of it to mortals.
.و کنترل آتش رو به انسان ها داد...
In essence, he gave us technology. He gave us power.
.اساساً , به ما تکنولوژی داد .به ما قدرت داد
So we're stealing fire? In the Arctic.
پس داریم آتیش رو از قطب شمال میدزدیم ؟
Actually, sort of. You see, whoever controls technology controls the world.
در حقیقت , تقریباً , ببین , هرکسی که .تکنولوژی رو کنترل بکنه , دنیا رو کنترل می کنه
The Roman Empire ruled the world because they built roads.
فرمانروایی رومی ها چون جاده ها رو .ساختند , در دنیا فرمانروایی می کردند
The British Empire ruled the world because they built ships.
فرمانروایی بریتانیا چون کشتی ها رو .ساختند بر دنیا حکمرانی می کردند
America, the atom bomb, and so on and so forth.
,آمریکا , بمب اتم رو ساخت .و غیره و غیره
I just want what Prometheus wanted.
.من فقط چیزی رو که تیتان خواست , میخوام
Sounds great, Lex, but you're not a god.
سخنرانی بی نظیری بود , لِکس اما تو خدا نیستی,
Gods are selfish beings who fly around in little red capes...
خدایان موجودات خودخواهی هستند ...که با شنل قرمزشون این اطراف پرواز می کنند
...and don't share their power with mankind.
و قدرت شون رو با ... .نژاد بشر سهیم نمیشن
Hey, boss.
.آهای , رئیس
We found something.
.یه چیزی پیدا کردیم
No, I don't wanna be a god.
.نه , نمیخوام خدا باشم
I just wanna bring fire to the people.
.فقط میخوام آتش رو برای بشر بیارم
And I want my cut.
.و سهمم رو میخوام
Was this his house?
این خونه اش بوده ؟
You might think so. Most would.
.ممکن بود همچین فکری بکنی .بیشتر سعی کن
This is more of a monument to a long dead...
...این بیشتر از یه مقبره برای یه مرگ طولانی
...and extremely powerful civilization.
. و تمدن خیلی قدرتمنده...
This is where he learned who he was.
.اینجا جائیه که فهمید کی بوده
This is where he came for guidance.
.اینجا جائیه که او برای هدایت نازل شد
Possibilities.
.احتمالاً
Endless possibilities.
.احتمالات نامحدود
You act like you've been here before.
.جوری رفتار می کنی انگار قبلاً اینجا بوده ی
My son...
...پسرم
... you do not remember me.
.منو بخاطر نمیاری...
I am Jor-El.
.من جور - اِل هستم
I'm your father.
.پدر تو
By now, I will have been dead many thousands of your years.
تا حالا , خیلی سال پیش از تو مرده ام
- He thinks I'm his son. - You are the only survivor of Krypton.
.فکر می کنه , من پسرشم- .تو تنها بازمانده ی کریپتون هستی-
Embedded in the crystals before you is the total accumulation of all literature...
جمع انباشته ی تمام ادبیات و فرهنگ و ...حقایق علمی از دوجین
... and scientific fact from dozens of other worlds...
جهان شناخته شده که ... ...مجموعاً 28 کهکشان شناخته شده
... spanning the 28 known galaxies.
.میشه , پیش از تو در بلورها انباشته شده...
There are questions to be asked.
.سئوالهای هستند که باید پرسیده شوند
Here in this...
...اینجا در این
This Fortress of Solitude...
... محل امن خلوت...
... we shall try to find the answers together.
بایستی سعی کنیم پاسخ ها... .رو با همدیگه پیدا کنیم
Can he see us?
میتونه ما رو ببینه ؟
No, he's dead.
.نه , او مرده
So, my son...
...خوب , پسرم
... Kal-El...
...کال-اِل...
... speak.
.حرف بزن...
Tell me everything...
...همه چیزو بهم بگو
...starting with crystals.
.با بلورها شروع کن...
Hey, boy.
.هی , پسر
- On Tuesday, between support...
.نگران نباش , امروز صبح دفنش کردم
- hindered the firefighting efforts for all those...
وادار کردن او به شهادت دادن پیش از .هیئت منصفه ی عالی تلاش بیهوده ای بود
Police have finally arrived and it's still complete mayhem down here.
Police have finally arrived and it's still complete mayhem down here.
Fighting broke out in the southernmost region...
Fighting broke out in the southernmost region...
... with border fire and small-arms attacks prevalent.
... with border fire and small-arms attacks prevalent.
Don't worry, I buried it this morning.
Don't worry, I buried it this morning.
- It was futile trying to force him to testify before a grand jury.
- It was futile trying to force him to testify before a grand jury.
Mom?
مامان؟
Five years.
.پنج سال
If your father was alive, he never would have let you go.
,اگه پدرت زنده بود .هرگز اجازه نمیداد بری
I almost gave up hope.
.تقریباً ناامید شدم
I just thought I would never see you again.
فقط فکر کردم .دوباره نمی بینمتون
Oh, Clark.
.اوه , کلارک
Did you find what you were looking for?
اون چیزی رو که دنبالش بودی , پیدا کردی ؟
I thought, hoped...
...نظرمنم همینه ,کاشکی
...it might still be there.
.هنوز اونجا باشه...
Your home?
خونه ات؟
That place was a graveyard.
.اونجا قبرستون بود
I'm all that's left.
I'm all that's left.
Clark, the universe is a big place.
.کلارک , جهان جای بزرگیه
And you don't know who's out there.
.و تو نمی دونی کی بیرون اونجاست
And even if you are the last...
...حتی اگر آخرین هستی
...you're not alone.
.تنها نیستی...
I know.
.میدونم
- Sorry. - Look out!
.ببخشید- !مراقب باش-
Watch out, will you?
مواظب باش , می تونی؟
- Excuse me. - Sorry.
.ببخشید- .متاسفم-
Sorry.
.متاسفم
Great. Would you be careful?
عالیه , ممکنه مراقب باشید ؟
- Jimmy. - Mr. Clark! I mean, Kent! Mr. Kent!
.جیمی- !آقای کلارک ! منظورم اینه , کنت ! آقای کنت-
Welcome back! Oh, my God!
!خوش اومدی ! اوه , خدای من
Hey, come... Wait right there. I'll be right back.
.سلام , بیا ... اونجا واسا .زودی برمیگردم
Oh, hey, sorry, guys, I'm still looking for a place to live...
,اوه ,سلام , ببخشید , آقایون ....اگه شما یه جای خوب می شناسین
...if you know of anything reasonable.
.هنوز دنبال یه جا واسه زندگی کردن می گردم...
Behind you, Mr. Kent. I made it myself. It's a cake.
.پشت سرت , آقای کنت .خودم درسش کردم , یه کیکه
Oh, it looks...
...اوه , بنظر میرسه
...delicious.
.خوشمزه ست...
Olsen! Where are the photos of that birthday-clown-massacre thing?
اولسن ! عکسهای چیز کجان؟
I'm on it, chief. Hey, look who's back.
روش دارم کار می کنم , رئیس هی , ببین کی برگشته,
- Kent? - Hey, chief.
کنت ؟- .سلام رئیس-
- Thank you for giving me my job back. - Don't thank me.
.ممنونم که شغلم رو بهم برگردوندید- .از من تشکر نکن-
Thank Norm Palmer for dying.
.از نورم پالمر برای مرگش تشکر کن
It was his time.
.وقتش بود
- Let's get you set up, huh? - Olsen!
بذار نشونت بدم , ها ؟- !اولسن-
Okay, so I gotta run...
...باشه , خوب آقای کنت , میخوام برم
...but I will be back to check on you in a sec, Mr. Kent.
اما یه ثانیه دیگه برمی گردم ... .تا دستی به سر و گوشت بکشم
Oh, hey, do you know where I can find Lois?
اوه , سلام , میدونی کجا می تونم لوئیس رو پیدا کنم؟
The timing of this automated-ignition countdown...
The timing of this automated-ignition countdown...
... is the most precarious part of the launch.
... is the most precarious part of the launch.
Lois Lane, Daily Planet.
Lois Lane, Daily Planet.
You also stated that the shuttle will usher in a new era of travel...
You also stated that the shuttle will usher in a new era of travel...
... enabling the average person to afford transcontinental flights.
... enabling the average person to afford transcontinental flights.
But can you tell us the exact price...
But can you tell us the exact price...
... an "average person" will be expected to pay?
... an "average person" will be expected to pay?
The answer to that question is in your press packet.
The answer to that question is in your press packet.
The Earth is surrounded by a blanket of air...
The Earth is surrounded by a blanket of air...
... which we call the atmosphere.
... which we call the atmosphere.
It reaches over...
It reaches over...
Yeah. He looks just like his mom.
.آره , ببین خیلی شبیه مادرشه
Already takes after her too, especially when it comes to getting into trouble.
مخصوصاً وقتیکه ناراحت میشه .خیلی شبیه ش میشه
Mother?
مادر؟
Oh, yeah, well, I guess you've been gone. Fearless reporter Lois Lane is a mommy.
.اوه , آره , حدس زدم رفته ای .گزارشگر نترس , لوئیس لین یه مادره
Oh, you know, I'll just... I'll take that. That's good.
...اوه می دونی , من فقط .انتخابش کردم . خوبه
- Sorry. - No. She's got plenty.
.ببخشید- .نه . او داره به مدارج بالا میرسه-
- Wait, she's married? - Yes.
واسا , ازدواج کرده ؟- .بله-
No. Not really. It's more like a prolonged engagement.
نه , راسش نه . بیشتر شبیه .یه نامزدیه طولانی مدته
But don't ask Miss Lane when they're tying the knot...
...اما ازش نپرس کی عروسی می کنن
...because she hates that question.
.چون از این سئوال متنفره...
- Like this follow the same stringent safety guidelines set by NASA?
- Like this follow the same stringent safety guidelines set by NASA?
Since this is a joint venture with the Air Force...
از وقتی که این یه ...تولید مشترک با نیروی هوائیه
You all right? You look like you could use a drink.
حالت خوبه ؟ بنظر میاد .نوشیدنی لازم داری
This place is so tacky. Why are we back here?
.اینجا خیلی رنگ و رو رفته س چرا به اینجا برگشتیم ؟
Kitty, while you were doing your nails and ordering fur coats online...
کیتی , وقتی تو داشتی رو ناخن هات کار ... می کردی و کت خز اینترنتی سفارش میدادی
...I was busy unlocking the secrets...
...سرگرم رمز گشایی  ...
...of one of the most advanced civilizations in the universe.
مهمترین تمدن پیشرفته ... .در دنیا بودم
Weren't there two of those?
دو تا از اونا اونجا نبودند؟
You see, unlike our clunky earthbound forms of construction...
بر خلاف شکل ساختمان های ...سنگین ریشه در زمین دوانده
...the technology on Krypton, Superman's home world...
,تکنولوژی در کریپتون... ...خونه جهانی سوپرمن
...was based on manipulating the growth of crystals.
برمبنای دستکاری در ... .رشد بلورها بود
Sounds like hocus-pocus to me.
.به نظر میرسه داری سرم رو شیره می مالی
Well, naturally, to the primitive mind, any sufficiently advanced technology...
خوب , طبیعتاً , برای انسان های ...اولیه , تفاوت میان تکنولوژی پیشرفته
...would be indistinguishable from magic.
.از جادو غیر قابل تشخیص خواهد بود...
But imagine: Cities, vehicles, weapons...
...اما تصور کن : شهر ها , وسائل نقلیه , اسلحه ها
...entire continents...
...قاره های دست نخورده...
...all grown.
.همه رشد خواهند کرد ...
To think that one could create a new world...
فکر کن یکی می تونست ...یه دنیای تازه ای با
...with such a simple little object.
.یه هدف خیلی ساده بسازه...
It's like a seed.
.شبیه یه بذره
And all it needs is water.
.و همه ی اونچه که احتیاج داره , آبه
Like...
...مثله
...Sea-Monkeys.
.چشم میمون...
Exactly, Kitty.
.دقیقاً کیتی
Like Sea-Monkeys.
.مثله چشم میمون
Clark has been doing a little soul-searching for the last couple years.
کلارک , ظرف دو سال گذشته .داشته یه کم خودکاوی انجام میداده
- He saw llamas. - Yeah?
.او ایلاماس رو دیده - آره؟-
- Yeah. - Must be tough coming back.
.آره- .باید برای برگشتن قوی باشی-
- Coming back? - To work.
برمیگرده؟- .کار-
Yeah.
.آره
Well, you know, things change.
.خوب , میدونی , بعضی چیزا تغییر می کنند
I mean, of course things change...
...منظورم اینه , البته که بعضی چیزها تغییر می کنند
...but sometimes things that you didn't think would change could change.
اما گاهی اوقات چیزهایی که فکرشو ... .نمی کنی تغییر کنند , تغییر می کنند
Take Lois.
.بگیر لوئیس
A woman like her, I never thought she'd settle down.
,یه زنی مثل او .هرگز فکر نمی کنه باید تنها بمونه
You know, if you ask me... Because she'll never tell you this...
...میدونی اگه از من بپرسی ...چون هیچوقت به تو نمیگه
...but if you ask me, she's still in love with you-know-who.
,اما اگه از من بپرسی... .او هنوز دوستت داره , میدونی کی رو می گم
The original space shuttle generated 7.5 million pounds of thrust...
فضای پیمای اصلی ...فقط در اولین مرحله ی
...just in the initial launch phase.
.فعالیتش 7.5 میلیون پوند فشار ایجاد کرد...
But, by piggybacking on this Boeing 777... Yes?
اما توسط یه بوئینگ 777 حمل میشه ... درسته ؟
If this launch is as pivotal as you claim...
...اگه این  کار اینقدر مهمه که تو میگی
...why is it being covered by one news network?
پس چرا فقط توسط یک ... شبکه خبری پوشش داده میشه؟
Why don't we save those questions for the post-launch briefing.
چرا شما سئوالاتونو واسه جلسه ی بعد از به کار انداختن نیگه نمی دارید؟
How about that, Miss Lane?
چطور بود , خانم لین؟
When we hit 40,000 feet, the shuttle will detach, ascend...
,وقتی وارد 40000 پایی میشیم ...فضا پیما جدا میشه ,بالا میره
...and then fire the first of two propellant systems, the liquid fuel boosters.
و سپس یکی از دو سیستم محرکه ... .تقویت کننده ی سوخت مایع , شروع به کار می کنه
When the shuttle reaches the stratosphere...
وقتی فضاپیما به طبقه فوقانی ...جو می رسه
...the secondary insertion booster will fire...
...دومین تقویت کننده روشن میشه...
...propelling the craft at 4gs into the mesosphere.
هواپیما رو با سرعت 4 جی اس  ... .به سوی لایه درونی جو سوق میده
- Careful. - I know.
.دقت کن- .میدونم-
- Careful. Careful.
.دقت کن . دقت کن-
Wow, that's really something, Lex.
.اوووم , واقعاً جالبه , لکس
Wait for it.
.حالا کجاش رو دیدی
It's freaking Gone With the Wind.
.احساس بر باد رفته رو دارم
- Shut off the camera. - But I'm getting it.
.دوربین رو خاموش کن- .اما دارم میگیرم-
I said, shut off the damn camera.
.گفتم , دوربین رو خاموش کن
I think I did something wrong.
.فکر کنم اشتباه کردم
No. That wasn't you.
.نه , اشتباه تو نبود
Ignition is at T minus one minute and we are prepping for separation.
احتراق یک دقیقه دیگه انجام میشه و .داریم برای تفکیک آماده میشیم
CDR, start the clock.
.سی دی آر , زمان رو شروع کن
Three minutes and counting.
.سه دقیقه و شروع کن
Body signs normal. Crew is looking good.
.نشانه های جسمانی عادیه . خدمه حالشون خوبه
Shuttle readouts are holding steady.
اطلاعات نمایش داده شده ی فضا پیما . وضعیت ثابتی رو نشون میده
- We're still a go for launch. - Roger.
.ما هنوز قصد پرتاب رو داریم- .باشه-
- Houston, you copy? - Houston, do you copy?
هیوستون , مفهومه؟-
Oh, God.
.اوه , خدایا
Electrical variance.
.مغایرت الکتریکی
What the...?
What the...?
Please, there's nothing to worry about.
خواهش می کنم , چیزی برای . نگران شدن وجود نداره
It seems that we are experiencing a slight power outage.
بنظر میرسه که ما داریم .یه قطع برق کم اهمیت رو تجربه می کنیم
- What did you do? - It wasn't me. It just cycled back up.
چیکار کردی؟- .من نبودم . من فقط پیشتیبان رو به جریان انداختم-
Genesis, radio check from Houston.
.جنسیس , بررسی ارتباط از هیوستون
There we have it. We were experiencing a power outage.
.صداتون رو داریم .داشتیم یه قطع برق رو تجربه می کردیم
- Climbing to 40,000 feet. - Roger, 40,000 feet.
.تا ارتفاع 40000 پائی بالا برید- .مفهوم شد . 40000 پائی-
And it's gone! A blazing fastball...
...و رفته ! یه گلوله ی سریع آتشین
Is that it?
خودشه؟
I don't think so.
.من اینطوری فکر نمی کنم
Dual engine failure, but they're up and running again.
,موتورهای دوگانه از کار افتاده اند .اما داریم دوباره سعی می کنیم به کارشون بندازیم
Genesis, I hate to say this, but it looks like we're gonna have to scrub the launch.
جنسیس , از گفتن این جمله متنفرم , اما .به نظر میرسه قصد داریم باید عملیات رو لغو کنیم
- Aborting booster ignition. - Roger. Aborting booster ignition.
.احتراق بالابرنده لغو میشه- .مفهومه , احتراق بالابرنده لغو میشه-
Boosters are non-responsive. We're still counting down for ignition.
.بالابرنده ها جواب نمیده .هنوز در حال شمارش معکوس برای احتراق هستیم
- Platform, we have a problem. - Go.
- Platform, we have a problem. - Go.
Looks like something faulted during the power outage.
Looks like something faulted during the power outage.
Both boosters are counting down for ignition.
Both boosters are counting down for ignition.
Platform, you have 30 seconds.
.بالابرنده , شما 30 ثانیه برای جدائی زمان داری
- What? - Release couplings.
- What? - Release couplings.
We can't shut down boosters.
We can't shut down boosters.
We should be able to manage the launch and recover to the emergency field.
باید قادر باشیم شروع رو به پیش ببریم .و بُرد اضطراری رو بدست بیاریم
T minus 23 seconds to ignition.
.تا احتراق 23 ثانیه
Genesis, you're a go for evac procedures.
Genesis, you're a go for evac procedures.
Twenty-one, 20...
...بیست و یک , بیست
... 19...
...نوزده...
Couplings are non-responsive.
.قسمت رابط جواب نمی ده
- We're still attached. - Seventeen.
.ما هنوز متصلیم- .هفده-
- Platform, couplings are jammed. - Fifteen.
.بالابر , قسمت رابط ایراد داره- .پانزده-
Fourteen.
.چهارده
Don't be alarmed. It's absolutely normal.
.نگران نباشید . کاملاً عادیه
We're still attached. Couplings are non-responsive.
.ما هنوز متصلیم .قسمت رابط جواب نمی ده
- Nine, eight... - Houston, can you do a remote override?
...نه , هشت- هیوستون , میتونید از دور جداش کنید ؟
... seven...
...هفت...
- Remote override is unresponsive. - ... six, five...
.جداسازی از راه دور جواب نداد- ....شش , پنج..
- I repeat, remote override is unresponsive. ...four, three...
.تکرار می کنم , جداسازی از راه دور جواب نداد- ...چهار , سه...
And if you're lucky, you may hear the faint pop of the sonic boom.
اگه خوش شانس باشید , شاید صدای شکستن .دیوار صوتی رو بشونین
- Houston, we have ignition. - Roger, ignition.
.هیوستون , موتورها روشنه- .مفهومه , روشنه-
- This is Python 21, she's pulling away. - Okay, all flight control is on the...
.پیتون 21 صحبت می کنه , داره خارج میشه- ...بسیار خوب , تمام کنترل هوایپما-
This is not a drill. Clear nonessential personnel.
.این یه تمرین نیس .وسائل غیر ضروری شخصی رو دور بندازید
Switch to emergency band frequencies.
.به فرکانس باند اضطراری عوض کن
Warning, warning.
.هشدار , هشدار
Oh, no! Oh, no!
!اوه , نه ! اوه , نه
Can I get a little help?
میتونم یه کمک کوچولوئی بکنم؟
This is UPV breaking news. From Washington, Frank Jacobs.
This is UPV breaking news. From Washington, Frank Jacobs.
We've just received word...
We've just received word...
... that the inaugural flight of the Genesis space shuttle...
... that the inaugural flight of the Genesis space shuttle...
... is experiencing a midair emergency.
... is experiencing a midair emergency.
- A problem with the launch of the new orbital shuttle, Genesis.
- A problem with the launch of the new orbital shuttle, Genesis.
The reports are telling us the shuttle failed to disengage...
The reports are telling us the shuttle failed to disengage...
... sending both crafts rocketing towards space.
... sending both crafts rocketing towards space.
We're now going live to Cape Canaveral for the latest update on this story.
We're now going live to Cape Canaveral for the latest update on this story.
Jim, all we know right now...
Jim, all we know right now...
... is that the couplings which hold the shuttle to the 777...
... is that the couplings which hold the shuttle to the 777...
... malfunctioned and did not release as planned.
... malfunctioned and did not release as planned.
- We're uncertain... - I should do...
- We're uncertain... - I should do...
... why the ignition sequence continued and boosters fired.
... why the ignition sequence continued and boosters fired.
However, there's speculation here that the blackout, which...
However, there's speculation here that the blackout, which...
Help me sit up.
.کمکم کن درست بشینم
Mach one. Still tied to the shuttle at 42,000 feet.
Mach one. Still tied to the shuttle at 42,000 feet.
- Houston, we need some help. Houston! - Running diagnostics check. Stand by.
-!هیوستون , احتیاج به کمک داریم . هیوستون- .امکانات عیب شناسی رو فعال کنید . آماده باشید-
Insertion booster ignition in five seconds.
.احتراق بالابرنده ی الحاقی در 5 ثانیه
Warning, warning.
Warning, warning.
What the hell is that?
این لعنتی دیگه چیه ؟
There's some kind of unidentified bogey coming from the north.
یه شی ء ناشناخته از سمت .شمال داره میاد
- Roger that. - And it's coming in fast.
.مفهومه- .و خیلی سریع حرکت میکنه-
Declaring an emergency.
.اعلام وضعیت اضطراری
Overspeed, overspeed.
.سرعت بالاتر از حد مجاز
Altitude...
Altitude...
Do you see that?
دیدیش؟
Fly up, fly up.
.برو بالا , برو بالا
Is everyone all right?
همه حالشون خوبه؟
Are you okay?
تو حالت خوبه؟
Well, I hope this experience hasn't put any of you off flying.
خوب , امیدوارم این تجربه شما رو .از پرواز کردن منصرف نکرده باشه
Statistically speaking, it's still the safest way to travel.
,به زبان آماری .پرواز کردن هنوز امن ترین راه برای مسافرت کردنه
Superman! Superman! Superman!
!سوپرمن ! سوپرمن ! سوپرمن
Superman!
!سوپرمن
Okay, everybody, listen up.
.خیلی خوب , همه تون , گوش کنید
I wanna know it all, everything.
.میخوام همه چیز رو بدونم
Olsen, I wanna see photos of him everywhere. No, I want the photos.
اولسن میخوام عکسهاش رو در هرجایی .ببینم . نه , من عکس میخوام
Sports, how are they gonna get that plane out of the stadium?
ورزش , چطوری میخوان اون هواپیما رو از تو اون استادیوم درآرند ؟
Travel, where did he go? Was he on vacation? If so, where?
مسافرت , او کجا رفت ؟ تو مرخصی بود ؟ اگه بود , کجا ؟
Gossip, has he met somebody? Fashion, is that a new suit?
شایعات , آیا با کسی قرار ملاقات داره ؟ لباس , لباسش جدیده ؟
Health, has he gained weight? What's he been eating?
سلامتی , چاقتر شده؟ چی میخورده ؟
Business, how is this gonna affect the stock market? Long-term, short-term.
تجارت , چطوری روی بازار بورس .تاثیر میذاره ؟ کوتاه مدت , دراز مدت
Politics, does he still stand for truth, justice, all that stuff? Lifestyle:
,سیاست , هنوزم برای حقیقت , عدالت :همه این چرندیات به پا میخیزه ؟ عنوان
"Superman Returns."
".سوپرمن باز می گردد"
Come on.
.یالّا
Gil, how many F's in "catastrophic"?
گیل , چند تا مسافر تو اون مصیبتند؟
None. What's the usage?
هیچی , کاربردش چیه ؟
"This mysterious electromagnetic pulse knocked out portable devices...
این جریان الکترو مغناطیس مرموز" ...دستگاه های قابل حمل
...and entire power grids, causing a catastrophic event during..."
,و تمام شبکه ی برق رو از کار انداخت... "...چون یه رویداد فاجعه آمیز
- Lois! - Yes.
!لوئیس- .بله-
In my office.
.برو تو دفترم
This goes for everyone.
.اینو به همه بگین
The story isn't the blackout, it's Superman!
,قصه قطع برق نیس !سوپرمنه
The story is the EMP, chief.
.رئیس , داستان جریان الکترو مغناطیسه
Every electronic device on the East Coast goes dark.
هر وسیله ی الکتریکی در .ساحل شرقی خاموش شده
- First, are you okay? - Yes, thank you.
اول از همه , حالت خوبه؟- .بله , ممنون-
Lois, three things sell papers: Tragedy, sex and Superman.
:لوئیس , 3 چیز باعث به فروش رفتن روزنامه ها میشه .فاجعه , سکس , و سوپرمن
People are sick of tragedy, we know you can't write worth a damn about sex.
میدونی که مردم دیوانه ی مصیبتند .چیزی با ارزش تر از فحش سکسی نمی تونی براشون بنویسی
That means one thing. That one thing is Superman. And you know it, Lois.
معنیش یه چیز ,  اون چیز هم .سوپرمنه , و تو میدونی لوئیس
Lois?
لوئیس؟
- Are you all right? You sure? - Yeah.
حالت خوبه ؟ مطمئنی؟- .البته-
- Yeah, I'm fine. - Thank God.
.البته که خوبم- . خدا رو شکر-
- Where's Jason? - I don't know. Isn't he with you?
جیسون کجاست ؟- نمی دونم . با تو نیست ؟-
- No. - Well, where is he?
.نه- خوب , پس کجاست ؟-
Hi.
.سلام
Who are you?
تو کی هستی ؟
I'm Clark Kent, an old friend of your mom's from before you were born.
من کلارک کنت هستم . یکی از دوستای قدیمی .مامانت , قبل از اینکه به دنیا بیای
Really? She never mentioned you.
.واقعاً ؟ هیچوقت راجع به تو چیزی نگفته
Really? Never?
واقعاً ؟ هیچوقت ؟
- No. - Jason.
.نه .جیسون-
- What are you doing here, honey? - Daddy's office is boring.
عزیزم , تو اینجا چی کار می کنی ؟- .دفتر بابا کسل کننده ست-
Daddy's office is boring?
دفتر بابا کسل کننده ست ؟
Clark, hey! Welcome back.
.سلام کلارک ! خوش اومدی
- I see you've already met the munchkin. - Yeah, we were just talking...
.می بینم قبلاً شازده کوچولو رو ملاقات کرده ی- ...اره , فقط داشتیم در مورد-
- Did you take vitamins? Eye drops? - Yes. Yes.
ویتامین هاتو خوردی ؟ قطره چشمیت رو ریختی ؟- .بله . بله-
- Albuterol? Poly-Vi-Flor? - Yes. Yes, Mom.
.بله , مامان
Good boy. He's a little fragile, but he's gonna grow up...
,پسر خوب . فقط یه کم ضعیفه ...اما میخواد بزرگ بشه
...to be big and strong like his dad, won't you?
مثله باباش قوی و بزرگ... بشه , اینطور نیست ؟
- Yes? - Yes.
آره ؟- .بله-
Oh, I saw you on the...
...اوه , تو تلویزیون دیدم
Oh, yeah. That was nothing.
.اوه , آره , چیز خاصی نبود
- Hey, can I borrow your stapler? - Oh, yeah.
میتونم ماشین دوختت رو قرض بگیرم؟- .بله -
Thanks.
.ممنون
Congratulations on the Pulitzer. That's incredible.
.به برنده ی جایزه پولیتزر تبریک میگم .باورنکردنیه
Yeah. Can you believe it? It's...
...آره . میتونی باور کنی ؟
So I wanna hear all about your trip.
.خوب میخوام همه چیز راجع به سفرت رو بشنوم
Where did you go? What did you see? Meet anyone special?
کجارفتی ؟ چی دیدی ؟ شخص خاصی رو ملاقات کردی؟
Well, there's so much. Where to begin?
خوب , خیلی زیاده , از کجا شروع کنم؟
Where's the little guy? Hey, kiddo.
.اون فسقلی کجاست ؟ هی بچه
- How are you? - Good.
حالت چطوره ؟- .خوبم-
Can you work some magic to get your uncle...
...میتونی عموتو خر کنی
...to stop giving me such a hard time on this article?
تا کار به این سختی ... روی این مقاله رو بهم نده؟
- Please? - Again?
خواهش می کنم؟- دوباره ؟-
- Again. - You got it.
.دوباره - .تو بُردی-
- How are you, kiddo? - Good.
حالت چطوره بچه ؟- .خوبم-
Oh, this is Clark.
.اوه , این کلارکه
- Clark, Richard. Richard, Clark. - Richard White.
.کلارک , این ریچارده . ریچارد این کلارکه- .ریچارد وایت-
Hi.
.سلام
Richard's an assistant editor here who's basically saved our International section.
ریچارد , دستیار ویرایشگر اینجاست , کسی که .اساساً بخش بین الملل ما رو نجات داد
He's also a pilot and he loves horror movies.
.در ضمن خلبانه و فیلم ترسناک دوست داره
Clark is...
...کلارک
Well, he's Clark.
.خوب , این کلارکه
Well, it's great to finally meet you. I've heard so much.
.خوب , خیلی عالیه که بالاخره شما رو دیدم .درباره تون زیاد شنیده م
- Oh, you have? - Yeah, Jimmy won't shut up about you.
اوه , واقعاً ؟- .آره , جیمی نمی تونه در مورد تو حرف نزنه-
- Gotta run. - Where?
.باید برید- کجا ؟-
You heard Perry. Superman's back, and he thinks I'm the only one equipped to...
شنیدی پری چی گفت . سوپرمن برگشته و ...و فکر می کنه من تنها کسی هستم که آماده شده م
To what?
برای چی آماده شدی ؟
- I don't know, you know. - So don't listen to him.
.میدونی که نمی دونم- .پس بهش توجه نکن-
I'm not. Going to the power plant to check out the blackout.
نمی کنم , میخوام برم نیروگاه برق در .مورد خاموشی اطلاعتی بدست بیارم
Okay.
.باشه
- Bye, Mom. - Bye.
.خداحافظ مامان- .خداحافظ-
- Bye, Lois. - And she's gone.
.خداحافظ لوئیس- .و او رفته-
No matter how close we are, that woman will always be a mystery.
,مهم نیست چقدر نزدیکیم .اون زن همیشه یه معما خواهد بود
If you need anything, I'm right over there.
,اگه چیزی احتیاج داشتی .من اونجام
Nice to finally meet you.
.خوشحالم که بالاخره دیدمت
Where do you wanna go? Wanna go to the park?
میخوای کجا بری؟ میخوای پارک بری؟
And he's got the whole world In his hands
و تمام دنیا در دستان اوست
He's got the whole world
تمام دنیا را در اختیار دارد
And he's got the whole world in his...
...و تمام دنیا در دستان
Oh, he's cute.
.اوه , جذابه
Run into trouble?
تو دردسر افتادین ؟
- Should see the other guy. - What are we gonna do?
.باید اونای دیگه رو هم میدیدین- میخوایم چی کار کنیم ؟-
Modify it, attach it to the stern.
.اصلاحش کن , ببندش به عقب کشتی
I don't care if the instructions are Russian.
.اهمیتی نمیدم که راهنماها روسی اند یا نه
- Lois? - Hey, Clark.
لوئیس؟- .سلام کلارک-
How does it feel to be back at work?
برگشتن سر کار چه احساسی داره ؟
Pretty good. You know, kind of like riding a bike, I guess.
,میدونی که خیلی خوبه .حدس میزنم تا حدی مثله دوچرخه سواری کردن باشه
- A bike? - Yeah, you know...
دوچرخه سواری؟- ...آره , میدونی که-
Never mind.
.بیخیالش
But I was wondering...
...اما در شگفت بودم
...since I've gotten back, we haven't really had a chance to catch up.
از وقتی که برگشته م ,شانس... .صحبت کردن رو نداشته یم
I thought maybe, if you'd like, we could go grab some food...
فکر کردم شاید , اگه دوست داشته ...باشی , میتونیم یه مقدار غذا دو دره کنیم
- Hey, can I ask you something? - Sure.
میتونم یه سئوال ازت بکنم ؟- .البته-
Have you ever met someone and it's like you're from different worlds...
تا حالا شخصی مثه خودت رو که از یه دنیای ...دیگه باشه رو ملاقات کردی
...but you shared such a connection you knew you were destined to be together?
اما در تقسیم یه ارتباط بدونی که... قسمت بوده با هم باشید؟
Then he just takes off without explaining why...
و بعدش بدون هیچ ...توضیحی یا بدون
...or without even saying goodbye?
یه خداحافظی بذاره بره؟...
Sounds cheesy, I know.
.حق با توئه , میدونم
- Well, maybe... - Taxi!
...خوب , شاید- !تاکسی-
...it was hard to say goodbye because he had to go...
خداحافظی کردن سخت بود... ...چون باید میرفت
...and he wanted to say goodbye, but maybe it was too difficult for him.
.,و میخواست خداحافظی کنه... .اما شاید براش خیلی مشکل بوده
Difficult? What's so difficult about it? "Goodbye." It's easy.
مشکل ؟ چی خداحافظی کردن اینقدر مشکله؟ "ساده ست , " خداحافظ
What's so hard about saying goodbye?
چی خداحافظی کردن اینقدر سخته ؟
Who are we talking about?
راجع به کی صحبت می کنیم ؟
Nobody, just forget I said anything.
.هیچکی , فقط هرچی گفتم رو فراموش کن
Taxi! Hey!
!آهای تاکسی
Taxi!
!تاکسی
Wow, thanks.
.باور نکردنیه , ممنون
312 Riverside Drive, please.
.خیابون ریورساید شماره ی 312 لطفاً
Good night, Clark.
.شب بخیر , کلارک
Superman!
!سوپرمن
I want egg rolls.
.من خوراک تخم مرغ میخوام
Nice try, kiddo. Only steamed chicken and snow peas for you.
انتخاب خوبیه , فسقلی , اما واسه تو .فقط مرغ آب پز و پوسته ی نخود زمستونیه
Why do we order Chinese if he's allergic?
اگه آلرژی داره , چرا غذای چینی سفارش میدیم؟
Because he loves the peas...
...چون او پوست نخود دوست داره
...and I think we all prefer egg rolls over macrobiotic shakes.
و من فکر می کنم همه ی ما خوراک تخم مرغ ... .رو بر عمر دراز مدت ترجیح میدیم
It's a good point.
.نکته ی خوبیه
So I noticed you've been acting a little different lately.
خوب متوجه شده ام تازگی ها .یه کم فرق کرده ی
Have I?
فرق کرده م ؟
You know, Lois, that article that you wrote.
,میدونی لوئیس .اون مقاله که نوشتی
"Why the World Doesn't Need Superman"?
"چرا دنیا به سوپرمن نیاز نداره؟"
No, no, no. No, the other one, from years ago, before we met.
,نه , نه , نه . نه اون یکی نه .چندین سال قبل , پیش از اینکه همو ببینیم
Which article? I wrote dozens about him. I was practically his press agent.
.کدوم مقاله ؟ یه دوجین مقاله راجع به سوپرمن نوشتم .عملاً مدیر مطبوعاتیش بودم
"I Spent the Night With Superman."
".یه شب رو با سوپرمن همخانه شدم"
Richard, come on.
.ریچارد , یالّا
It was the title of an interview.
.عنوان مقاله این بود
Plus, it was your Uncle Perry's idea.
.بعلاوه , نقشه ی عموت , پِری بود
- No, I know, I know. It's okay, it's okay. - Richard.
.نه , می دونم , میدونم . ایرادی نداره- .ریچارد-
It was a long time ago.
.اون ماله خیلی وقت پیش بود
Were you in love with him?
عاشقش بودی ؟
He was Superman. Everyone was in love with him.
.او سوپرمن بود .همه عاشقشند
But were you?
اما تو هم عاشقش بودی؟
No.
.نه
Lois, I shouldn't have brought it up.
.لوئیس , نباید این بحث رو پیش می کشیدم
Even though you've been raised as a human being...
...اگرچه از انسان بودن , بالاتر رفته ای
... you are not one of them.
.اما یکی از اونا نیسی...
They can be a great people, Kal-El. They wish to be.
.اونا میتونن مردمان فوق العاده ای باشن , کال-ال .آرزو می کنن باشن
They only lack the light to show the way.
اونها فقط به نور هدایت .احتیاج دارن
For this reason above all, their capacity for good...
,بنا بر همه دلایل بالا ...ظرفیتشون برای خوبی
... I have sent them you...
...تنها پسرم رو ...
... my only son.
.براشون فرستاده ام...
Load them up.
.بیارشون بالا
Holy sh...
...خدای من
Attention, the Metropolis Museum of Natural History...
...توجه , موزه ی تاریخ طبیعی متروپولیس
... will be closing in 10 minutes. We hope that you've...
.ظرف 10 دقیقه بسته خواهد شد... ...امیدوارم که شما از
Sir, we're closing in 10 minutes.
.آقا , 10 دقیقه دیگه  می بندیم
We only need five.
.فقط 5 دقیقه وقت میخوام
You're done, the museum's closed. Thank you.
.کارتون تموم شده . موزه بسته است .ممنون
Are you all right, miss?
حالتون خوبه , دوشیزه ؟
- My heart. I... I... - I'm sorry?
...قلبم . من ... من- ببخشید ؟-
I have a palpitation, a heart palpitation. And a murmur.
,من تپش قلب دارم
Please, take me to the hospital.
.خواهش می کنم , منو ببر بیمارستان
Take me to the hospital.
.منو ببر بیمارستان
Just hold on tight.
.فقط محکم بچسب
Bingo.
.جانمی جان
- There you are, ma'am. - My heart.
.بفرمائید , خانوم- .قلبم-
My palpitations, they're gone. What did you do?
.تپش قلبم , خوب شد تو چیکار کردی ؟
I didn't do anything.
.هیچکاری نکردم
Call me Katherine.
.کاترین صدام کن
Katherine. I'm glad you're feeling better.
.کاترین , خوشحالم که حالت بهتره
- You have places to go, people to save? - Yes.
جائی رو داری بری , مردم رو نجات بدی؟- .بله-
Would you like to get a cup of coffee sometime?
دوست داری یه زمانی یه فنجان قهوه باهام بخوری؟
- I know that's forward. Or a drink? - Good night.
میدونم گستاخانه ست . یا مشروب؟- .شب بخیر-
Good night.
.شب بخیر
It's like this on every channel.
.همه ی شبکه ها همینطوریه
He was in Manila at 10:55 p.m. And then spotted...
.ساعت 10:55 ب.ظ تو مانیل ( پایتخت فیلیپین ) بود ...و سپس علامت گذاری شده
- Hey, Kent, chief wants to see you. - Oh, thanks.
.سلام , کنت , رئیس میخواد ببینتت- .اوه , ممنون-
But as this security footage from a simple deli robbery proves...
But as this security footage from a simple deli robbery proves...
... there's really no feat too big or too small for the Man of Steel.
... there's really no feat too big or too small for the Man of Steel.
Reports are flooding in from Metropolis, Houston, Gotham and as far...
Reports are flooding in from Metropolis, Houston, Gotham and as far...
Satellites have proven most ineffective at tracking him.
Satellites have proven most ineffective at tracking him.
He might literally be moving near the speed of light.
He might literally be moving near the speed of light.
- Our map is illuminated with sightings... - Kent!
- Our map is illuminated with sightings... - Kent!
- The chief is waiting. - ... on every continent, giving citizens...
- The chief is waiting. - ... on every continent, giving citizens...
These are iconic, and they were taken by a 12-year-old with a camera phone.
اینا رو یه پسر 12 ساله با .یه گوشی دوربین دار گرفته
- What do you got, Olsen? - I got those.
تو چی گرفتی , اولسن؟- .اینا رو -
- Look, in the sky, chief. - It's a bird.
.رئیس , آسمان رو ببین- .یه پرنده ست-
- It's a plane. - No, look, it's...
.هواپیماست- ...نه , ببین , اون-
You wanted to see me?
میخواستید منو ببینید؟
Yeah, Kent, come on in. Sit down.
.آره , کنت , بیاتو , بشین
I wanna talk a little strategy. Okay.
.میخوام یه کم با استراتژی صحبت کنم .خوب
First off, Lois, I don't understand what you're doing...
اول از همه , لوئیس , نمی فهمم ...چیکار داری می کنی
...sneaking around covering the blackout. - It wasn't just a blackout.
.دزدکی قطع برق رو پوشش میدین... .اون فقط یه قطع برق نبود-
Cell phones, pagers, automobiles, airplane...
,تلفن های همراه , پیجرها ...اتومبیلها , هواپیماها
Every other paper in town has got a female reporter...
,همه ی روزنامه های دیگه ی شهر ...یه خبرنگار زن دارند
...a good-looking female reporter, stashed on the roof covering Superman.
,یه خبرنگار زن خوش قیافه... .رو پشت بوم جمع میشند و سوپرمن رو پوشش میدن
- And you two are the ones with history. - Chief, I've done Superman.
.و شما 2 تا با یه داستان مشغولید- .رئیس , من کارم با سوپرمن تموم شده-
Covered him. You know what I mean.
.پوششش بده , میدونی که منظورم چیه
Yeah, that makes you an expert. Do him again.
.آره , اینکار تو رو کار کُشته ت می کنه .دوباره پوششش بده
- There are a dozen other stories out there. - Yeah? Name one.
.یه دوجین داستان اون بیرون هست- .آره ؟ یکی رو اسم ببر-
Well, there was a museum robbery last night.
خوب , دیشب از موزه تاریخ طبیعی .دزدی شده
Even Superman missed that one. He was too busy saving this hooker.
.حتی سوپرمن هم اونو از دستش داده .خیلی سرگرم نجات دادن اون فاحشه بوده
Why don't you guys track down Lex Luthor?
چرا از کسائی نمیخوای جای لکس لاتر رو بدست بیارند؟
Well, no one's seen him since his fifth appeal.
خوب , هیچکی بعد ازپنجمین .استینافش ندیدتش
He's got more history with Superman than anyone.
او بیش از هرکسی با .سوپرمن قضایا داره
Maybe he's got something to say.
.شاید یه چیزی واسه گفتن داره
- Luthor's yesterday's news. - No, I like that idea.
.خبرهای دیروز لاتر- .نه , من اون نقشه رو دوست دارم-
Perry, Lex Luthor is a career criminal who nearly killed him, for God's sakes.
پِری , لکس لاتر یه مجرم حرفه ئیه .که محض رضای خدا , تقریباً اون رو کشت
Jimmy, how did Lex Luthor get out of prison?
جیمی , لکس لاتر چطوری از زندون در اومد؟
Well, the appeals court called Superman as a witness and he wasn't around.
خوب , در دادگاه استیناف از سوپرمنخواستند به عنوان . شاهد در جایگاه شهود حاضر بشه و اون نشد
How much do you think that pisses off Superman?
, فکر می کنی چقدر سوپرمن ناراحت بشه ؟
- Give him to someone else. - A lot.
.اینو بده به یکی دیگه- .خیلی زیاد-
- Polly. Give him to Polly.
.پولی , بدش به پولی-
Lois, Superman.
.لوئیس , سوپرمن
- What about the blackout? - Kent, blackout.
درباره قطع برق چی میدونی؟- .کنت , رو قطع برق کار کن-
Great. Thanks, chief.
.عالیه . ممنون رئیس
Lois, I'm sorry. I'd hate if this damaged our relationship.
لوئیس , متاسفم . اگه این به ارتباطمون .صدمه بزنه , باهاس متنفر باشم
Relationship?
ارتباط؟
- Yeah. - Hi, Mommy.
.آره- .سلام مامان-
- Hi, you. - Hey, guys.
.سلام بر تو- .سلام آقایون-
He got an A in science, but a D in gym, so we're doing something right.
,یه نمره ی قبولی تو علوم داشت , اما ورزشت رو رد شد .پس داریم به یه جاهائی میرسیم
- Yeah, at least one of us is. - What?
.آره , حداقل یکی از ماست- چی؟-
It's Perry. He just shoved Superman back into my life.
پریه . او سوپرمن رو به .زندگیم برگردوند
Well, honey, I'm sure you can find a way to interview Superman...
خوب , عزیزم , مطمئنم یه راهی ...واسه مصاحبه با سوپرمن پیدا می کنی
...without bringing him back into your life.
بدون اینکه مجبورش کنی... .به زندگیت برگرده
There's really no way around it, folks. Superman is back in all of our lives.
.واقعاً هیچ راهی نیس .سوپرمن به زندگیهامون برگشته
We're coming to you from Sydney...
...ما از سیدنی میام
... where people have gathered on these rooftops to scour the sky...
جائیکه مردم رو پشت بامهاشون جمع شده بودن... ...و آسمان رو می گشتند
Okay, how about this? We'll stay late. We'll get dinner.
باشه , در مورد این چی فکر می کنی؟ .تا دیروقت می مونیم . شام میخوریم
I'll help with Superman, and you and Clark can work on the blackout together.
من در مورد سوپرمن بهت کمک میکنم و توهم میتونی .با کلارک روی خاموشی ها کار کنی
- Is that all right with you, Clark? - Swell.
همه چیز مرتبه , کلارک ؟- .عالیه-
I was gonna pretend the brakes were out.
داشتم وانمود می کردم که .ترمز ها نمی گیرند
Pretend. Like we talked about.
وانمود کن . همونطوری که .راجع بهش صحبت کردیم
You didn't actually have to cut them!
!واقعاً نباید می بریدشون
Of course I did.
.معلومه که مجبورم
A man can always tell when a woman is pretending, especially Superman.
یه مرد علی الخصوص سوپرمن موقعی که یه زن وانمود می کنه , همیشه میتونه بگه
So did you get your rock?
خوب سنگ رو بدست آوردی؟
I did.
.آره
U.S. Coast Guard issuing a small-craft advisory for the Metropolis ocean area.
U.S. Coast Guard issuing a small-craft advisory for the Metropolis ocean area.
High-wind advisory is in effect...
High-wind advisory is in effect...
... ocean currents and tides becoming increasingly dangerous.
... ocean currents and tides becoming increasingly dangerous.
All warnings lasting until later this evening.
All warnings lasting until later this evening.
Security, security.
Security, security.
This is U.S. Coast Guard issuing a small-craft advisory for northeast seas.
This is U.S. Coast Guard issuing a small-craft advisory for northeast seas.
Winds reaching 50 miles per hour, high tides in the morning.
Winds reaching 50 miles per hour, high tides in the morning.
Waves reaching 20 to 30 feet.
Waves reaching 20 to 30 feet.
This warning is in effect for all small crafts for the next four hours.
This warning is in effect for all small crafts for the next four hours.
Weird. If these times are right...
...عجیبه , اگه این بار حق با اوناست
...the blackout spread from a specific origin point.
.قطع برق از یه منبع مشخص منتشر میشه...
Where?
کجا ؟
I'm not sure yet.
.هنوز مطمئن نیستم
With the super-hearing, does he hear each sound by itself or everything at once?
,با شنوایی ویژه , او میتونه بوسیله منبع صدا رو یا هرچیزی رو فوراً بشونه؟
Both.
.هردو
- He's certainly taller than I thought. - 6'4".
.از اونچه فکر می کردم بلند تره- - 6'4".
I love that he can see through anything. I'd have fun with that.
.دوست داریم او میتونست از بین هر چی ببینه .بایستی با اون سرگرم باشم
Anything but lead.
.هرچیزی به جز رهبری
- I bet he's... - 225 pounds...
...شرط می بندم او- ...وزنش 225 پوند-
...faster than a speeding bullet...
...سریعتر از سرعت یه گلوله ...
...draws his power from the sun, invulnerable to anything but kryptonite...
,قدرتش رو از خورشید میگیره... ...از هرچیزی مصونه بجز کریپتون
...and he never lies. - Kryptonite?
.و هرگز دروغ نمیگه... کریپتون ؟-
Radioactive pieces of his home world.
.قطعات رادیو اکتیویته از خونه اش
It's deadly. To him.
.که براش کشنده ست
Lois, how tall would you say Clark is?
لوئیس , میگی قد کلارک چقدره ؟
About 6'3", 6'4".
.در حدود 6.3 , 6.4
About 200, 215 pounds?
بین 200 تا تا 215 پوند وزنشه ؟
Jimmy, Jason, let's go get these intrepid reporters something to keep them going.
جیمی , جیسون , این خبرنگارای نترس چیزی .واسه موندن دارن , بزن بریم ببینیم چیه
- Burritos! - Come here, canhead.
!بوریتوس - .بیا اینجا-
We're going this way. Do they have anything other than burritos?
ما از این طرف میریم , به جز بوریتوس چیز دیگه ای داری؟
I think they have fries and burgers.
.فکر می کنم سیب زمینی سرخ شده و همبرگر دارن
So have you found a place to live yet?
هنوز یه جا واسه زندگی پیدا نکردی؟
No. I'm still looking.
.نه , هنوز دنبال می گردم
You know, Lois, I wanted to ask you about that artic...
میدونی لوئیس , میخواستم ازت ...راجع به این مقاله بپ
Hey, I'm gonna run downstairs for some fresh air. Great!
سلام , دارم میریم طبقه بالا !یه هوایی تازه کنم . عالیه
Thanks.
.ممنون
- Let's talk when I get back. - Sure.
.بذار وقتی برگشتم صحبت کنیم- .البته-
You know, you really shouldn't smoke, Miss Lane.
میدونین خانم لین , شما .واقعاً نباید سیگار بکشید
- Sorry. Didn't mean to startle you. - I'm fine. Really.
.ببخشید , نمی خواستم بترسمونت- .من خوبم-
I just wasn't expecting you.
.فقط انتظارشو نداشتم
With all the press on the plane...
...با همه ی خبرنگارها تو هواپیما
...I wasn't sure it was the best time for us to talk.
مطمئن نبودم که بهترین ... .وقت برای صحبت ما بود
Well, there's no press around now. Except for me, of course.
خوب , هیچ روزنامه نگاری البته .به جز من این اطراف نیست
I know people are asking questions now that I'm back.
میدونم حالا که برگشتم مردم .میخوان سئوالاتی بپرسن
I think it's only fair that I answer those people.
فکر کنم منصفانه ست که .پاسخ این افراد رو بدم
So you're here for an interview?
پس اومدی اینجا که مصاحبه کنی ؟
Okay, then.
.باشه
- Where did I put that thing? - Right pocket.
اون چیزو کجا گذاشتم؟- .جیب راستت-
Let's start with the big question.
.بذار با سئوال بزرگ شروع کنیم
- Where'd you go? - To Krypton.
کجا رفتی ؟- .به کریپتون-
But you told me it was destroyed. Ages ago.
اما بهم گفته بودی که خیلی .وقت پیش از بین رفته
It was.
.درسته
But when astronomers thought they found it...
اما وقتی ستاره شناسان گمان کردند ...اونها پیداش کردند
...I had to see for myself.
.باید خودم میدیدمش...
Well, you're back, and everyone seems to be pretty happy about it.
خوب , تو برگشتی , و همه به نظر .میرسه از برگشتنت خوشحالن
Not everyone.
.نه همه
- I read the article, Lois. - So did a lot of people.
.من , مقاله رو خوندم لوئیس- .خوب خیلیا خوندن-
- Tomorrow they're giving me the Pulitzer... - Why did you write it?
...فردا جایزه پولیتزر رو بهم می- چرا نوشتیش ؟-
How could you leave us like that?
چطور تونستی  اونطوری ترکمون کنی؟
I moved on. So did the rest of us.
.من موندم . مثه باقی افراد
That's why I wrote it.
.این دلیله نوشتنمه
The world doesn't need a savior.
.دنیا به ناجی احتیاج نداره
And neither do I.
.منم همینطور فکر می کنم
Lois.
.لوئیس
Will you come with me?
باهام میای ؟
Why?
واسه چی؟
There's something I wanna show you.
.یه چیزی هست که میخوام نشونت بدم
Please.
.خواهش می کنم
I can't be gone long.
.نمی تونم مدت زیادی بیرون باشم
You won't be.
.نیستی
Clark said the reason you left without saying goodbye...
کلارک گفت چون هضم این مسئله ...واسه شما سخت بوده
...is because it was too unbearable for you.
بدون خداحافظی اینجا رو... .ترک کرده
Personally, I think that's a load of crap.
.شخصاً فکر می کنم خیلی مزخرفه
- Clark? - He's just a guy I work with.
کلارک؟- .شخصیه که باهاش کار می کنم-
Maybe Clark's right.
.شاید حق با کلارک باشه
You know, my...
...میدونی , من
Richard, he's a pilot. He takes me up all the time.
.ریچارد , خلبانه .همیشه منو با خودش بالا می بره
Not like this.
.البته نه اینطوری
I forgot how warm you were.
.فراموش کردم چقدر داغ بودی
Listen.
.گوش کن
What do you hear?
چیزی میشنوی؟
Nothing.
.هیچی
I hear everything.
.همه چیز میشنوم
You wrote that the world doesn't need a savior...
تو نوشتی که دنیا به ...ناجی نیاز نداره
...but every day I hear people crying for one.
اما هر روز ... .صدای کسایی رو که صدام می کنن , میشنوم
I'm sorry I left you, Lois.
.ببخشید ترکت کردم , لوئیس
I'll take you back now.
الان برت می گردونم
Richard's a good man.
.ریچارد مرد خوبیه
And you've been gone a long time.
.و تو یه مدت طولانی غیب شده بودی
I know.
.میدونم
I...
...من
So will I see you around?
پس این دور و بر می بینمت ؟
I'm always around.
.همیشه همین دور و برم
Good night, Lois.
.شب بخیر , لوئیس
We're having beef, honey. Do you want the tofu wrap or the veggie wrap?
داریم گوشت میخوریم , عزیزم میخوای تو توفو بپیچم یا تو سبزی؟
You all right?
You all right?
Where have you been?
کجا بوده ی؟
I was up on the roof, getting some air.
.بالا رو پشت بام بودم . رفتم یه هوایی بخورم
Tell the truth now.
.راسش بگو
Were you smoking?
سیگار می کشیدی؟
No.
.نه
Is this real?
راست میگی؟
- Where'd you find him? - He found me.
کجا پیداش کردی؟- .او پیدام کرد-
Oh, this is great. I can't wait to read it.
.اوه , عالیه . برا خوندنش نمی تونم صبر کنم
So, Mr. White, about the blackout...
...خوب , آقای وایت , درباره ی قطع برق
Lois, this is the biggest night of your life.
لوئیس , امشب , بزرگترین .شب زندگیته
Have you picked out a dress? Something snazzy?
لباس انتخاب کردی؟ یه چیز جذاب؟
It just feels a little weird winning for that article.
فقط یه کم احساس عجیب و .غریب واسه بُردن اون مقاله می کنم
- It just doesn't seem right. - What doesn't seem right?
.به نظر میرسه یه چیزی درست نیست- چی درست نیست ؟-
Winning an award for an article called "Why the World Doesn't Need Superman."
واسه یه مقاله با عنوان " چرا دنیا به .سوپرمن نیاز نداره " جایزه بردم
When, according to this newspaper, they do.
در حالیکه , بر طبق .این روزنامه , اونا انجامش دادن
Lois, Pulitzer Prizes are like Academy Awards.
لوئیس , جایزه ی پولیتزر مثه .جایزه ی اسکار می مونه
Nobody remembers what you got one for. It's just that you got one.
.هیچکی یادش نمیاد واسه چی جایزه رو بردی .فقط می دونن که بردی
- But... - This is your night. You enjoy it.
...اما- .امشب , شب توست . ازش لذت ببر-
I'm sure Kent's on the blackout.
.مطمئنم کنت پشتمه
Department of Water and Power, please.
.بخش آب و برق , لطفاً
7782, great.
.خوب , 7782 , عالیه
Metropolis Public Works.
.تاسیسات عمومی متروپولیس
Hi, Stephen, Lois Lane from the Daily Planet. Blackout?
سلام , استفان , لوئیس لین از روزنامه ی پلانت هستم . خاموشیه؟
I just need a little info on a few outstanding power grids.
فقط یه کم اطلاعات مهم در مورد .منطقه برق میخوام بدونم
Yeah, I do have it here, actually.
.آره , در حقیقت, اینجا دارمش
So the uptown grid went dark at 12:36 and midtown 10 seconds before.
پس منطقه ی بالای شهر ساعت 12:36 قطع شد .و برق مرکز شهر هم 10 ثانیه قبل رفت
Which grid was hit first?
کدوم منطقه اول  رفت؟
It just reads Vanderworth.
.فقط وندورث میخونه
- Across the river? - 6 Springwood Drive.
سرتاسر رودخونه؟
6 Springwood Drive. A residence or a business?
یه اقامتگاه یا محل کار ؟
- Residence. - Sure? Nothing before that?
.اقامتگاه- مطمئنی ؟ هیچی قبل اون ؟-
- That's all it shows. - Thank you very much.
.همش همینه - .خیلی ممنون-
Oh, Jason.
.اوه , جیسون
- There's your mom, Jason. - You're late, Mommy.
.مامانت اینجاست- .دیر کردی , مامان-
Where are we? Is this the Pulitzer?
کجائیم ؟ اینجا محل توزیع جوایز پولیتزره؟
Nope. I've just gotta ask these people a few questions and then we can go.
نوچ . فقط میخوام از اینا چند تا سئوال .بپرسم , بعدش می تونیم بریم
Can I stay in the car?
میتونم تو ماشین بمونم؟
No, honey.
.نه , عزیزم
- Are we trespassing? - No. Yes.
داریم غیر قانونی وارد میشیم ؟- .نه . آره-
Hello?
آهای؟
I like the curly one.
.اون فرفریه رو دوست دارم
Let's go. This was a bad idea.
.بزن بریم . نقشه ی بدی بود
Lex Luthor.
.لِکس لاتر
Lois Lane?
لوئیس لین؟
You're bald.
.تو کچلی
And what is your name?
و اسم شما چیه؟
I'm not supposed to talk to strangers.
.اجازه ندارم با غریبه ها حرف بزنم
- Cute kid, and smart. - Thanks.
.بچه ی باهوش و زیبایه- .ممنون-
We're not really strangers, are we? This is kind of a little reunion.
ما که غریبه نیستیم , هستیم ؟ .این یه نوع تجدید دیدار کوچولوئه
Heck, I'm a fan.
.من یه طرفدارم
I love your writing...
...نوشته ها و
...and your dress. - I love your boat.
.و لباستو دوست دارم... .منم قایقتو دوست دارم-
How'd you get it? Swindle some widow out of her money?
چطوری گیرش آوردی؟ کلاه بیوه ها رو برداشتی؟
That's funny. Didn't you win the Pulitzer Prize...
عجیبه .جایزه ی پولیتزر ...رو برای محبوب ترین
...for my favorite article of all time, "Why the World Doesn't Need Superman"?
مقاله ی زندگیم با عنوان " چرا دنیا به... به سوپرمن نیاز داره ؟" رو نبردی
Didn't you have a few more years to go on that double life sentence?
نباید یه چند سال دیگه ادامه میدادی تا حکم حبس ابد 2 برابر شه ؟
Yes, well, we can thank the Man of Steel for that.
بله , خوب , می تونیم از .مرد آهنین برای اینکارش تشکر کنیم
I mean, he's really good at swooping in and catching the bad guys...
منظورم اینه , کارش در سریع پائین اومدن و ...گرفتن آدم بدا واقعاً خوبه
...but he's not so hot at the little things, like Miranda rights...
,اما در یه سری کارهای کوچیک موفق نیس , مثله حقوق میراندا... (قانونی که شهروند در هنگام دستگیرشدن از حقوق خودش آگاه باشه)
...due process, making your court date.
آئین های دادرسی قانونی که حق هر ... شهروندیه , مشخص کردن تاریخ دادگاه
Did you have anything to do with the blackout?
با قطع برق ارتباطی داشتی ؟
Are you fishing for an interview, Miss Lane?
داری  سعی می کنی مصاحبه کنی  , خانم لین ؟
It's been a while since you've been a headline.
خوب از وقتی که تیتر اول روزنامه ها .بوده ئی ,آرزوی داشتم
Maybe it's time people knew your name again.
شاید وقتشه مردم دوباره .اسمت رو بدونن
How about we turn this boat around, call a cab for my son...
,نظرت چیه این قایق رو برگردونیم ...یه تاکسی واسه پسرم بگیری
...and then you can do whatever you want with me.
.و بعدش هرکاری ... .دلت خواست میتونی باهام بکنی
No, I don't think we'll be turning around, Miss Lane...
...نه , فکر نمی کنم بتونیم دور بزنیم خانم لین
...which means that we do have some time to kill.
منظور اینه که ... .برای کشتن وقت داریم
How about that interview?
نظرت درباره ی مصاحبه چیه ؟
Yeah, just call me if you hear anything. Okay. Thank you.
.آره , اگه چیزی شنیدی , بهم زنگ بزن .باشه , ممنون
So, what did the school say?
خوب , مدرسه چی گفت؟
She picked him up at 3: 15.
.ساعت 3:15 دقیقه بردتش
- Hi, I heard about Lois. - Yes, come in, Clark, come in.
.سلام , راجع به لوئیس شنیدم- .آره , بیا تو , کلارک , بیا تو-
- Is there anything I can do? - Yeah, you're a reporter.
کاری هست که بتونم انجام بدم؟- .البته , تو یه خبرنگاری-
- Help Richard track her down. - I'll check her computer.
.به ریچارد کمک کن اون زنو پیداش کنه- .یه نیگاهی به رایانه بنداز-
Excuse me, Clark.
.ببخشید , کلارک
What do you know about crystals?
در مورد بلورها چی میدونی؟
They make great chandeliers.
.با اونا چلچراغای بزرگ میسازند
This crystal may seem unremarkable, but so is the seed of a redwood tree.
,این بلورها شاید عادی به نظر برسه .اما مثله دانه ی یه درخت چوب قرمزه
It's how our mutual friend in tights made his Arctic getaway spot.
چطوریه که دوست مشترکمون (سوپرمن ) تو .اون لباس تنگ , نقطه فرارش رو تو قطب شمال ساخت
Cute. It's a little small for my taste.
.جالبه . فقط برای من یه کم کوچیکه
You're building an island?
داری یه جزیره میسازی؟
You're not seeing the big picture here, Miss Lane.
خانم لین , شما این عکس به این .بزرگی که اینجاست رو نمی بینی
Let me enlarge it for you.
.بذار برات بزرگش کنم
Not just an island, an entirely new continent.
,این فقط یه جزیره نیس .یه قاره ی کاملاً جدیده
An extinct world, reborn on our own.
.یه دنیای مرده , دوباره در درون ما متولد شد
Why?
چرا ؟
Land, Miss Lane.
.زمین , خانم لین
I mean... Kitty, what did my father used to say to me?
منظورم اینه ... کیتی پدرم عادت داشت چی بگه؟
"You're losing your hair"?
"تو داری کچل میشی؟"
- Before that. - "Get out"?
.قبل از اون- "برو بیرون؟"-
He said, "You can print money...
...او می گفت " تو می تونی با ساختن
...manufacture diamonds, and people are a dime a dozen...
,الماسای تقلبی , پول چاپ کنی... ...و اونا معمولی میشن
...but they'll always need land."
". اما اونا همیشه به زمین احتیاج دارن...
It's the one thing they're not making any more of.
یه چیز هست که .دیگه ازش تولید نمی کنن
But the United States...
...اما ایالات متحده
Will be underwater.
.زیر آب خواهد بود...
It's simple physics, Miss Lane.
.این یک قانون ساده ی فیزیکه , خانوم لین
Two objects cannot occupy the same space at the same time.
دو چیز نمی تونن در یک زمان .و یک فضای مشخص قرار بگیرن
And the rest of the world will just let you keep it?
و باقیمونده دنیا فقط بهت اجازه میدن نیگهش داری؟
- They'll...
...اونها-
...what?
چی؟...
I'll have advanced alien technology...
...تکنولوژی هزاران ساله ی پیشرفته ی بیگانه ها رو
...thousands of years beyond what anyone could throw at me.
که هرکی می تونست برام بندازه ... .رو در اختیار خواهم داشت
Bring it on!
! ادامه بده
And eventually...
...و نهایتاً
...the rest of the world will be begging me...
باقیمونده ی دنیا... ...ازم التماس خواهند کرد
...for a piece of high-tech beachfront property.
تا بهشون قطعه ای از تکنولوژی... .پیشرفته رو بهشون بدم
In fact, they'll pay through the nose for it.
در حقیقت , اونا قیمت .بالایی برای این خواهند داد
But millions of people will die.
.اما میلیون ها میلیون انسان خواهند مرد
Billions! Once again, the press underestimates me.
,میلیون ها میلیون ! یکبار دیگه .مطبوعات منو دستکم گرفتند
This is front-page news.
.این سرصفحه ی اخباره
Come on, let me hear you say it just once.
یالّا , بذاز فقط یکبار بشنوم .تو این رو میگی
- You're insane. - No! Not that. No, the other thing.
.تو دیونه ای- .نه ! نه , نه-
It's dangling off the tip of your tongue. Let me hear it just once, please?
.زبونت رو قورت دادی خواهش می کنم , بذار یه بار بشنوم ؟
- Superman will never... - Wrong!
...سوپرمن هرگز- !اشتباهه-
What is that?
اون چیه ؟
I think you know exactly what this is.
.فکر کنم میدونی دقیقاً این چیه
Mind over muscle, Miss Lane.
.بر روی عضلاتت تمرکز کن , خانم لین
Mind...
...تمرکز کن
Who is that boy's father?
بابای این بچه کیه ؟
Richard.
.ریچارد
Mr. Luthor, we're approaching the coordinates.
.آقای , لاتر , به این مختصات نزدیک میشیم
Are you sure?
مطمئنی ؟
Yes, sir. Latitude 40 degrees north, longitude 73 degrees west.
,بله قربان . عرض جغرافیائی 40 درجه ی شمالی .طول جغرافیائی 73 درجه ی غربی
Don't let them leave this room.
.نذار این اتاق رو ترک کنن
Kitty, come with me. You're not gonna want to miss this.
.کیتی , باهام بیا .نمیخوام از دستت بدم
- Damn it. - What?
.لعنتی- چیه؟-
She has a password.
.یه رمز عبور داره
"Jason."
"جیسون"
"Richard."
"ریچارد"
Try "Superman."
سوپرمن " رو امتحان کن"
"Superman." Great.
.سوپرمن " . عالیه"
Don't touch that, honey.
.بهش دست نزن , عزیزم
Why don't you go play the piano.
.چرا نمیری پیانو بزنی
Come on, come on, come on.
. یالّا , یالّا , یالّا
Lex, this isn't like the train set.
.لِکس , این مثه مجموعه ی قطار نیس
I know.
.میدونم
Come on, come on.
.یالّا , یالّا
Come on.
.یالّا
- Honey, are you okay? - Yeah.
عزیزم , حالت خوبه؟- آره-
- Are you hurt? - I'm fine.
زخمی شدی؟- .خوبم-
Open this door! Open it!
!درو باز کن ! بازش کن
Could you help Mommy open the door?
میتونی کمک مامانت کنی درو باز کنه؟
I'm sorry.
.متاسفم
It's gonna be okay.
.اوضاع رو به راه میشه
Okay? It's gonna be okay.
.خوب ؟ اوضاع رو به راه میشه
We had a little problem downstairs.
.طبقه پائین یه مشکل کوچولو داشتیم
Brutus is dead.
.بروتوس مرده
He got hit with the piano.
.با پیانو له شده
Where's the boy?
پسره کجاست ؟
With the mother, locked up in the pantry.
,با مامانشه .تو انبار زندونین
Oh, it's time for us to go.
.اوه , وقتشه بریم
My camera's not working.
.دوربینم کار نمیکنه
And my phone's not working.
.تلفنم هم کار نمی کنه
- Okay, I'm good. - That was weird.
.خوب ,من خوبم- .غیرعادی بود-
Hey, guys. This just came through the fax.
.هی آقایون .این از فکس اومد
It's Lois' handwriting, I'd recognize it anywhere.
,دست خط لوئیسه .هرجا ببینمش تشخیص میدم
I just... No idea what the numbers mean.
من فقط ... نمی دونم .این شماره ها چه مفهومی دارن
- They're coordinates. - Coordinates.
.اینا مختصاتند- .مختصات-
That's just off the coast.
.اینا درست خارج ساحله
Jimmy, tell Perry I'm taking the seaplane. Keep trying her cell.
.جیمی , سعی کن به پری زنگ بزنی .بگو دارم یه هواپیمای دریائی میگیرم
What are these, lottery numbers?
اینا چیند , شماره های قرعه کشی؟
I think they're coordinates, chief.
.فکر کنم اینا مختصاتند , رئیس
Chief...
...رئیس
Come on! Move it!
!یالّا ! تکونش بده
Chief!
!رئیس
Great Caesar's ghost.
.روح سزار کبیر
- Daddy. - Oh, my God.
.بابا- .اوه خدای من-
How did you get here?
چطوری اومدی اینجا ؟
I flew.
.من پرواز کردم
Look out!
!مواظب باش
Mom!
!مامان
Mom! Mom!
!مامان ! مامان
Jason, come here! Jason!
!جیسون , بیا اینجا ! جیسون
Come here! Watch your head! Come here!
!بیا اینجا ! مراقب سرت باش !بیا اینجا
Mommy! Mom!
!مامان!مامان
Jason!
!جیسون
Jason, hold on!
!جیسون , وایسا
- Have you got him? - I got him! Go!
گرفتیشون ؟- !گرفتمشون ! برو-
Hold on! Hold on!
!وایسا ! وایسا
- Mommy! - Give him to me!
!مامان- !بدهش من-
Mommy!
!مامان
- Mommy! Mommy! - Come on, Jason! Come on!
!مامان !مامان- !یالّا , جیسون ! یالّا-
- Lois! Lois! - Mommy!
!لوئیس ! لوئیس- !مامان-
Jason, get on my back.
.جیسون , برو رو پشتم
Give me your hand.
.دستتو بده
- Have you got them? - Yeah.
اونا رو آوردی؟- .بله-
Get buckled in!
!کمربندا رو محکم ببندین
She'll be fine.
.حالش خوب میشه
I can't take off in this.
.اینطوری نمی تونم بلند شم
- I'll point you in the right direction. - Thank you.
.درستش میکنم- .ممنون-
See anything familiar?
همه چیز آشناست؟
I see an old man's sick joke.
.یه جوک مزخرف از یه پیرمرد می بینم
Really? Because I see my new apartment...
واقعاً ؟ چون آپارتمان ...جدیدمو می بینم
...and a place for Kitty, one for my friends...
,و یه جا واسه کیتی... ...یکی واسه دوستام
...and that place over there, I'll rent out.
.و اونی که اونجاست , رو میخوام اجاره کنم...
But, you know, maybe you're right. You know, maybe it is a little cold.
.اما , میدونه که , شاید حق با تو باشه .میدونی , شاید یه خورده سرده
It's... What's the word I'm searching for? It's a little...
کلمه ای که دارم دنبالش می گردم چیه ؟ ...یه کم
...alien.
.غریبه ست...
It lacks that human touch.
. از اون نوازشهای انسانی احتیاج داره
You have something that belongs to me.
.یه چیزهای دستته که مال منه
Metropolis Tower, this is seaplane November-Seven-Two-Four-One-Hotel.
برج متروپولیس , این هواپیمای .دریائی هتله 7241 نوامبر
Do you copy?
مفهومه؟
Metropolis Tower, this is seaplane November-Seven-Two-Four-One-Hotel.
برج متروپولیس , این هواپیمای .دریائی هتله 7241 نوامبر
Do you copy? Damn it!
!مفهومه؟ لعنتی
Metropolis Tower, this is seaplane November-Seven-Two-Four-One-Hotel.
برج متروپولیس , این هواپیمای .دریائی هتله 7241 نوامبر
Do you copy?
مفهومه؟
Lois! Are you all right?
لوئیس ! حالت خوبه ؟
Yeah. What happened?
آره . چی شده ؟
- Superman. - Where is he?
.سوپرمن- کجاست؟-
He went back.
.برگشت
- Richard, we have to turn around. - What? No.
.ریچارد , باید دور بزنیم- .چی ؟ نه-
- We have to turn around! - We barely made it out of there.
!میخوام برگردی- .به سختی از اونجا در اومدیم-
- Now you want me to go back? - Yes, please!
حالا ازم میخوای برگردم ؟- !بله , خواهش میکنم-
He'll die.
.او میمیره
All right, hold on.
.بسیار خوب , طاقت بیار
Kryptonite.
.کریپتون
You're asking yourself, "How?"
از خودت سئوال می پرسی , "چطوری" ؟
Didn't your dad ever teach you to look before you leap?
پدرت یادت نداده قبل اینکه کاری بکنی , فکر کنی ؟
Crystals. They're amazing, aren't they?
بلورها , فوق العاده ان , اینطور نیس ؟
They inherit the traits of the minerals around them...
همانطور که پسر از پدر ...خصوصیاتش رو به ارث میبره
...kind of like a son inheriting the traits of his father!
بلورها خواص مواد معدنی ... !اطرافشون رو به ارث می برند
You took away five years of my life, I'm just returning the favor!
,تو 5 سال از عمرم رو از بین بردی !میخوام لطفتو جبران کنم
I'm still Superman!
!من , هنوز سوپرمنم
Get up! Come on!
!پاشو ! بجنب
Now, fly.
.حالا , پرواز کن
So long, Superman.
.به امید دیدار , سوپرمن
Your leadership can stir others...
... رهبری تو میتونه سایرین رو به
... to their own capacities for moral betterment.
سمت بهبود اخلاقی خودشون... .سوق بده
The human heart is still subject to monstrous deceits.
قلب انسان هنوز هم موضوع .اغفال های غول پیکره
Our destruction could have been avoided. At this very moment...
.تباهی ما میتوست اجتناب ناپذیر باشه ...در این لحظه ی خاص
... I could embrace you in my arms.
.کاش می تونستم در آغوشت بگیرم...
Your help would be called for endlessly. Remember me.
.کمکت بی وقفه درخواست میشه .منو بخاطر بیار
Even for those tasks which human beings could solve themselves.
حتی برای اموری که نژاد انسان .خودشون میتونه حلش کنه
Remember me, Kal-El.
.کال اِل , منو بخاطر بیار
Remember me.
.منو بخاطر بیار
Superman's down there.
.سوپرمن اون زیره
- You sure? - Yeah.
مطمئنی ؟- .آره-
- Richard! - Yeah, I saw him. Strap in.
!ریچارد- .آره , دیدمش , کمربنداتون رو محکم کنید-
Lois!
!لوئیس
Don't move.
.تکون نخور
Come on, come on, come on.
.یالّا , یالّا , یالّا
Richard!
!ریچارد
I'm trying! It's too choppy!
!سعی می کنم ! خیلی پرتلاطمه
Oh, my God.
.اوه , خدای من
How did you find me?
چطوری پیدام کردی؟
Thank you.
.ممنون
What are you doing?
چیکار می کنی؟
I have to go back.
.باهاس برگردم
You're hurt!
!تو زخمیی
Goodbye, Lois.
.خداحافظ , لوئیس
The technology on Krypton, Superman's home world...
,تکنولوژی کریپتون ...خانه ی سوپرمن
... was based on manipulating the growth of crystals.
بر مبنای دستکاری کردن... .در رشد بلورها بود
Sounds like hocus-pocus to me.
.به نظر میرسه سرم رو شیره می مالی
Well, naturally, to the primitive mind, any sufficiently advanced technology...
خوب , طبیعتاً , برای انسان های ...اولیه , تفاوت میان تکنولوژی پیشرفته
... would be indistinguishable from magic.
.از جادو غیر قابل تشخیص خواهد بود...
But imagine: Cities, vehicles, weapons...
...اما تصویر : شهرها , وسایل نقلیه , اسلحه ها
... entire continents, all grown.
.تمام قاره ها  , همه بزرگ میشند...
Lex?
لِکس؟
Are billions of people really going to die?
آیا میلیون ها میلیون انسان واقعاً دارن می میرن؟
Yes.
.بله
Lex, what's happening?
لِکس , چی شده؟
Go, go, go. Get to the helicopter.
.برو , برو , برو , سوار هلیکوپتر شو
Go! Out, out! Now!
!برو , بالا , بالا ! حالا
No, no, no, take nothing! Take nothing! Go, go!
!نه , نه , نه , عکس نگیرین !عکس نگیرین ! برو ! برو
Got it.
.بگیرش
Here.
.اینجا
- What did you do? - I'm sorry!
تو چیکار کردی؟- !متاسفم-
No!
!نه
- What did you do? - I'm sorry!
تو چیکار کردی؟- !متاسفم-
Watch it.
!مراقب باش
- Clear a path. - Clear the way.
.راه رو باز کنید-
- Move! - Trauma One.
!بجنبید- تروما وان-
- Where we going? - Trauma One. Here it is.
کجا داریم میریم؟- .تروما وان . اینجاست-
Watch it!
!مراقب باش
Got him!
!گرفتمش
Okay, I think I got it.
.بسیارخوبی , گرفتمش
Penetrating side wound to right part of lower back.
Penetrating side wound to right part of lower back.
No hemorrhage.
.هیچ خونریزی نیس
Shock at 200.
.شوک 200 ولت
Is that enough? He's not human.
.کافیه ؟ او انسان نیس
All right, charge to three, 360.
.بسیار خوب , بذارش روی 3 , 360
Clear!
!واضح شد
It's kind of morbid, Perry.
.یه نوع بیماریه , پِری
Always be prepared.
.همیشه آماده باشید
How is she?
حالش چطوره ؟
Thank you. Thanks, baby.
.ممنون . ممنون عزیزم
- Lois? - Yeah.
لوئیس ؟- .بله-
We can leave whenever you're ready.
.هروقت آماده ای می تونیم بریم
I mean...
...منظورم اینه
...you don't have to be here.
.تو نباید اینجا باشی...
Where else would I be?
کجا باید باشم؟
Police have surrounded the area in order to control thousands of visitors...
پلیس با کنترل هزارن بازدید کننده ...که اومدن حمایت خودشون رو نشون بدن
... who have arrived to show their support.
.منطقه رو احاطه کرده است...
Many are carrying signs and banners...
...خیلی ها دارند نشانه ها و علامت هایی با خود حمل می کنند
I could drive.
.میتونم رانندگی کنم
- No official announcements over the past few hours...
هیچ گزارش رسمی در چند ...ساعت گذشته نشده
... but unconfirmed reports from inside tell us...
اما شنیده ها از داخل ... ...بیمارستان حاکی بر اونه
... the Man of Steel lies in a coma...
...مرد آهنین هنوز در کماست...
... his condition unchanged since he was admitted late yesterday.
شرایطش از دیروز که پذیرفته... .شده , هیچ فرقی نکرده
- Doctors have been vigilant in their... - Foreign exchange markets...
...دکترها گوشه به زنگ بوده اند- ...خرید و فروش ارزهای خارجی-
- Where are you going? - To the hospital.
کجا میری ؟- .بیمارستان-
I'd be careful down there, guys. It's a madhouse.
.مراقب پائین اونجا باشید , آقایون .اونجا یه دیوونه خونه ست
- So much for parking. - Do you think I can get in?
فکر می کنی می تونم برم تو؟-
You're Lois Lane. They'll let you in.
.شما لوئیس لین هستید . شما اجازه دخول دارید
I wanna go with Mommy.
.میخوام با مامان برم
Taxi.
.تاکسی
I'll be right here.
.اینجا خواهم بود
Watch your head, okay? Here we go.
.مواظب سرتون باشید , باشه؟از این طرف
This way, Miss Lane.
.از این طرف , دوشیزه لین
Mommy? Is he gonna get better?
مامان ؟ بهتر میشه ؟
- I don't know. - I want him to.
.نمی دونم- .میخوام خوب شه-
I like him.
.دوسش دارم
Me too.
.منم همینطور
I don't know if you can hear me.
.نمی دونم می تونید از من بشنوید
They say sometimes that when people are...
گاهی اوقات میگند ...موقعیکه مردم
That sometimes they can hear you.
.هستند اون موقع می تونن درکت کنن
I don't know if you can hear me.
.نمی دونم می تونید از من بشنوید
I wanted to tell you...
...میخواستم بهت بگم
Come on, honey.
.یالّا ,عزیزم
Step back, please!
!عقب واسا , لطفاً
Lex, we only have six of those!
!لکس , فقط شش تا از اینا داریم
Six?
شش تا ؟
I would trade 300,000 coconuts...
...میخواستم 300000 تا نارگیل رو
...and every ounce of your blood...
...و هر اونس از خونت رو ...
...for a quart of gasoline!
!با یه لیتر بنزین عوض کنم...
But what will we have to eat?
اما چی باید بخوریم؟
You will be different.
.تو متفاوت خواهی بود
Sometimes, you will feel like an outcast.
.گاهی اوقات , احساسی شبیه یه آواره داری
But you'll never be alone.
.اما هرگز تنها نخواهی بود
You will make my strength your own.
.تو قدرت منو مال خودت خواهی کرد
You will see my life through your eyes...
......زندگیم رو از درون چشمهات خواهی دید
...as your life will be seen through mine.
.همونطوری که زندگیت از طریق... .چشمهای من دیده خواهد شد
The son becomes the father...
...پسر , پدر میشه
...and the father becomes the son.
.و پدر صاحب پسر میشه...
Good night!
!شب بخیر
I...
...من
Will we see you?
دوباره می بینیمت؟
Around?
دور و بر ؟
I'm always around.
.همیشه همین دور و برم
Good night, Lois.
.شب بخیر , لوئیس